Chapter 1: Something of a Riddle

Author's Note

Hello everyone,

This is my AU/Continuation of Harry Potter and the Methods of Rationality. Chapter One takes the place of HPMOR Ch. 105. This story takes a different approach to HPMOR, especially with regard to Quirrell (who is not leather-pantsed: he still casts AK at will), the Philosopher's Stone, and the endgame.

Many thanks to the Reddit user /u/kulyok for her services as beta.

Tom Riddle.

The words seemed to echo inside Harry's head, sparking resonances that as quickly died away, broken patterns trying to complete themselves and failing.

Tom Riddle is a

Tom Riddle was the

Riddle

Professor Quirrell briefly looked expectant, but then the expression was gone. "And though I must credit your deduction, Mr. Potter - or Riddle, as the case may be - it is a little more complicated than that."

"I," Harry croaked, "what do you mean?"

The Defence Professor sighed, and his shoulders dropped, but the gun and the wand remained perfectly steady, the eyes sharp and icy. "I had rather hoped, Mr. Potter, that that would now be clear to you. No matter, we have time." His lips curled into a customary small smile. "If it puts you at ease, suffice it to say that you are only mostly Voldemort. As for me... well. Something of a riddle, Mr. Potter."

A note of hope soared in Harry's breast, buoyed still further by the fact that the Professor was upright and verbose, before his inner Slytherin shot it out of the sky in its anti-wishful-thinking instinct. Even if the Defence Professor wasn't evil it was still in his best interests to stay on guard.

Harry opened his mouth to say something - he wasn't sure what. Professor Quirrell... didn't gesture with the gun, but it suddenly somehow seemed far more prominent.

"Now. I obviously do not want to kill you, Mr. Potter, so please relax to the extent that it is reasonable to do so when a perfect Occlumens is pointing a gun at you and assuring you that he means no harm."

Harry tensed even further, and that earned him the ghost of a grin.

"I must apologise for threatening you, Mr. Potter, but you do have a staggering anti-talent for meddling." The Defence Professor's voice became clipped. "When I tell you to do so, you are going to remove your Time-Turner, which you will seize by the chain. You will then remove your pouch and emergency portkeys, and hand everything to me. We are both considering loopholes in that, so allow me to say that I have raised anti-Portkey wards, and if I do suspect that you are doing anything untoward I shall be forced to shoot you in the arm. I do not wish to harm you, but you have tourniquets in your pouch and are a good enough Occlumens to ignore the pain. Begin."

Harry swallowed and obeyed.

Harry's time machine disappeared into the flowing professorial robes, and the spares stored in his pouch floated up and deposited themselves in pockets and around the Professor's neck. Professor Quirrell pointed his wand at the pouch and muttered something vaguely Latinate, then handed it back to Harry. The gun vanished as though it had never been.

The Defence Professor smiled. "Now, Mr. Potter, today we are going to follow in the footsteps of every child in Gryffindor and a handful of the staff, and delve into a hideously dangerous maze of traps set by the greatest wizard alive. Doesn't that sound like fun?"

Some people are so likeable it's hard to hate them properly, said Draco's imagined voice in Harry's mind.

But he implied he's not Voldemort - if we can get the Stone Professor Quirrell might not die -

Waves of relief were washing through Harry, so powerful that he felt like laughing. The idea that he was wrong, that Quirrell was not the Dark Lord, and that he might not have to lose a friend again...

At that thought, Harry recalled watching Hermione Granger as her heart failed for lack of blood, as magic fled her broken shell and carried her mind with it.

He remembered Lily Potter's last stand, how she'd died with her wand in her hand, how Voldemort had stood over the corpse of a hero and laughed.

He remembered the story of the man who called for his country to unite, and the skins nailed to the wall.

He remembered the statistics, thousands dead by Voldemort's hand alone - that is, he thought about Hermione, and tried to multiply that feeling by a thousand.

And then he locked cold green eyes on the entity before him. Professor Quirrell was possibly Voldemort in some way, and that meant he couldn't afford to be happy yet.

All right. Back to being sane now.

Hermione's voice in his head was telling him not to trust Quirrell... Voldemort... Quirrellmort? Harry ignored the bizarre urge to laugh again. It was just nervousness and relief, and he didn't need that. Hermione was supported by half of Hufflepuff, the other half of which was standing up for Harry's friend and mentor. Ravenclaw was trying to remember where it had heard "something of a riddle" before. Harry set all of that aside. How can I get the truth from someone who plays "one level higher than you"?

"Mr. Potter, in all seriousness, I am indeed dying. The unicorn will sustain me only long enough for this. The Philosopher's Stone is located here, and it has power beyond what, I suspect, Dumbledore knows. Dumbledore may be able to twist himself into opposing immortality, but if he knew the healing it truly could do, he would have seized it from Flamel long ago. As you must have guessed, I need your help, Mr. Potter. I realise that it is... impolite to threaten one's friends with firearms, but I hope you'll understand, given that my life is at stake."

Harry cleared his throat and clicked a stronger, calmer, sombre aspect into place. "If Lord Voldemort has a reputation for telling the truth, Professor, I have not heard it."

"Which is why it is fortunate that you are not speaking to Lord Voldemort, Mr. Potter. Not quite, at any rate."

Hope-

That's exactly what the Dark Lord Voldemort WOULD say, hissed Hufflepuff and Slytherin.

Harry shut the thought down, and considered how to ask why he should believe the Professor without offending him.

"Ssnakess can't lie," hissed Professor Quirrell.

What?

"Two pluss two equalss four." Harry had tried to say "three". How does this work... Harry mustered the strongest Occlumency barrier he could. "Green ssmellss like-" Harry couldn't make any further Parseltongue pass his lips. "Interesting." How does Parseltongue determine the truth? Could I guess Interdicted lore by trying different statements until one of them worked, or is it just things I think are true? If that's the case, could a False Memory Charm beat it?

"Honesstly do not hold ill will towardss you. Am not truly Dark Lord in meaningful ssensse. No particular tasste for ssensseless murderss, though admit that value placcced on mosst livess iss not commenssurate with that of mossst moralisstss. Sseek Sstone to ssave own life, iss devicce of great healing power."

Harry paused.

The drowning sense of horror had drained away, and the overwhelming relief was replaced by growing pressure.

He needed more time, he couldn't make a decision so quickly, couldn't just change his whole viewpoint again in a few seconds...

Harry ignored his brain.

Voldemort or not, the Defence Professor was not a good man. He never had been, Harry had always known that. He could cast the Killing Curse at will, would probably not lose much sleep over murdering anyone who seriously annoyed him...

But... it was idealism, sheer foolish idealism, but... he was also Harry's friend.

You didn't just give up on friends even when they were this badly wrong, not while you had a chance of saving them.

You certainly didn't let them go off and pose a risk to other people.

You didn't allow them to die through your own inaction, either.

And it wasn't as though he had much of a choice.

"All right, Professor. Let's go and get that Stone."

OoOoO

"Professor?" asked Harry as they came to a halt directly before the polished oaken door. "What exactly does the Stone do?"

Harry had mastered his breathing, now, and he saw the Defence Professor clearly. The man's cheeks were sunken and his limbs thin and his skin grey - the sickness hadn't all been bluff... unless Quirrell was an exceptional actor and a wizard, which he was. Of course, he could just want the Stone for...

... other reasons...

"An excellent question, Mr. Potter, and one I found myself asking. Consider, if you will, a witch or a wizard with a heart blacker far than the Dark Lord's, selfish and jealous of their ancient device, a key not only to immortality but also to enormous healing power, such that they withhold it from all. Consider also that Dumbledore, master and servant of a Phoenix, holds this person as a close personal friend."

"Flamel is a perfect Occlumens who convinced Dumbledore that he needed to keep the Stone away from people?"

"Of course. And clearly, one such as he would not tell the truth to the greatest wizard in the world, but he might enjoy leaving hints. So, Mr. Potter, bearing in mind that Flamel creates specifically gold, true gold, and lives six hundred years, and the world still does not run on happy stories, and this device is truly unique and of ancient power, what does the Philosopher's Stone do?"

"It makes other magic permanent," replied Harry almost automatically. It might have just been a guess, or it might have been some half-remembered speculation from one of the few texts on the Stone, or maybe it was the fact that gold did not tarnish or fade like lesser metals. It felt like a certain guess, along the lines of the truth about Dementors or the secret of the Killing Curse. Harry was beginning to suspect that there was some subtle secondary effect of the Interdict, lest magic ever be truly lost...

"Quite so. The Philosopher's Stone will render a Transfigured item the true substance, and grant permanence to Charms and rituals. This is is a power beyond almost any other magic. There are some very few spells and items that are truly enduring, others such as the castle Hogwarts that are sustained by a constant well of magic, and many that are fleeting, but the Philosopher's Stone imparts true endurance to any magic. Naturally, this will save my life, and I will gladly assist you in using the Stone to resurrect the late Miss Granger. Sstone truly impartss permanenccce, sshall usse it to raissse girl-child-friend."

Harry's heart did not stop, because that would be an absolutely ridiculous evolutionary adaptation, but it seemed a very accurate metaphor.

Harry started to smile. The Defence Professor was not the Dark Lord, he might actually really be able to save Hermione... if Harry had been holding a wand at that moment, he thought, he might have burned away all the Dementors of Azkaban from where he stood.

"I assume you Transfigured Miss Granger's corpse into the ring on your finger? The diamond would be the more obvious option to check, and its magic would mask that of the ring."

Harry was struggling to stay properly pessimistic. "As a certain someone would say, Professor, not paranoid enough. I hoped people would assume that, and when they tested it and failed it would provide a second layer of cover. I Transfigured her into as big a diamond toe-ring as I could, to minimise Transfiguration damage, and just hid her under my pillow when Dumbledore summoned me."

As it happened, Dumbledore had never checked the ring. It seemed likely that he had simply sensed that it was wholly mundane. Harry's recently-unlocked Time-Turner had allowed him to hide Hermione's corpse before his bed was inspected.

"Cunning indeed. Now, Mr. Potter, rest assured that we have time. Our discovery here would raise quite the hue and cry, and since your Quidditch game went uninterrupted it seems likely it shall not come to pass. Still, it does not do to tarry in any case." Professor Quirrell gestured at the door.

Harry took a deep breath and readied himself, conscious as ever of the hard weight on his left foot.

Chapter 2: Playing Chess, Pt 1

The oaken door swung open, and -

Harry didn't bother to stop himself from screaming as he threw himself backwards and away from the triplicate sets of glinting teeth. He landed, not hard enough to hurt a wizard, and drew his wand and roared "Stupefy! Stupefy!"

The first stunbolt dazed the creature slightly, but before the second hit home a chunk of Hogwarts' stone wrenched itself free of the floor and flew into the path of the spell. The levitation visibly left it just before the bolt hit, and then it melded back into the floor.

"Not bad as a reaction, Mr. Potter," said Professor Quirrell's somehow-audible voice over the creature's many-voiced roar, "but consider that Dumbledore designed this chamber as a game for eleven-year-olds." A genuine-looking smile. "Before he ever saw an army of them. This creature, which our intrepid groundskeeper informs me is named Fluffy, is Charmed to spit students out without harming them. Now, how do you suggest we deal with this most terrifying of creatures?"

"Ah," Harry said as he tried to slow his heartbeat down, "if, um, Fluffy is like Cerberus in Greek mythology, because that phrase is not ridiculous at all, then we could sing to it?"

Professor Quirrell was giving him a look.

The Killing Curse is unblockable, unstoppable, and works every single time on everything with a brain.

"Um. We might trigger alarms by going in all wands blazing?"

"That was a flimsy excuse, but very well."

A flick of the Defence Professor's wand, a sound like a hundred songs played backwards in the space of a second, and Fluffy collapsed in a snoring heap.

"As for alarms, Mr. Potter," said Professor Quirrell, "the race between magical defence and offence is a decisive win for offence, which is why modern cursebreakers can pierce the tombs of ancient wizards, and so I confess myself impressed that Dumbledore's wards took me many months to untangle." He gestured Harry forwards. "After you."

Harry entered the chamber before his brain caught up with him, and he turned to behold a more-evil-than-usual smirk. Harry swallowed, trying not to imagine what his parents would say.

The room was high and dim, lit only by small, high windows set into recessed alcoves. The stone was grey and coarse, cemented together roughly, more like a ruined Muggle fortress than the rest of the castle Hogwarts. "Lumos," Harry muttered, focussing the light into a narrow beam like a torch, and began to inspect the featureless alcoves.

"What are you doing, Mr. Potter?"

"Searching the room. There could be some sort of inscription, or a key we'll need later, or a hidden passageway, or-"

Professor Quirrell massaged his temples briefly. "As it happens, your mastery of Muggle role-playing games might serve you well if you ever feel the urge to enter the Tomb of Amon-Set, but I remind you once again that Dumbledore built this game, this false puzzle, for first-years."

"Ah."

Harry skirted the drooling Cerberus and eased open the worn trapdoor, which disappointingly failed to creak eerily.

The pit dropped far below, he couldn't tell how far but it looked a long way below ground level, insofar as that meant anything in Hogwarts. He thought he caught a glimpse of something wriggling at the very bottom.

"Broomstick" said Harry to his pouch, and he climbed on and gestured Professor Quirrell towards the back seat.

Professor Quirrell floated gently into the air.

Harry noticed his confusion. "I thought wizards couldn't levitate themselves?"

"Quite so. It is said to be like lifting oneself up by one's own bootstraps. And indeed, one of the Dark Lord's most feared feats was to fly like smoke on the wind, unsupported but for his own wizardry. How did he and I do this, boy? Answer as quickly as you can."

I'm sorry, are we really still buying that he isn't Voldemort? asked Slytherin.

He swore he wasn't, in Parseltongue, spoke Ravenclaw, although admittedly it still probably isn't a good idea to trust him. So what do we know that has the power to fly?

"Um... you cast broomstick enchantments... no, you had someone else cast broomstick enchantments on your underwear, then Obliviated them."

"Cloth would not hold the magic. Broomstick enchantments must be cast on a long, narrow, rigid shape."

Perhaps Harry had been spending too much time around the older Ravenclaws, because he had to fight down a snicker at that. "How long does it have to be? Could you just strap short broomsticks to your arms?"

"Indeed, I did at first. And yet..." Professor Quirrell rolled up his sleeve to reveal a bare, wasted arm.

Harry raised an eyebrow. "You have broomstick enchantments on your bones?"

"And in thirty seconds of creativity, Mr. Potter, you have solved what has been called one of the greatest challenges of modern wizardry." A shake of the head. "Even after much study of the Muggle arts of psychology and some curious Legilimency, I have yet to discover just what is wrong with ordinary people, that they do not seek to optimise what they see. If only the lore of the legendary Felix Felicis were not lost to the ages... but I digress."

Professor Quirrell flew neatly down into the pit, and Harry followed.

Carefully avoiding a patch of what Harry recognised as Devil's Snare, they came to another stone chamber. The air was filled with a metallic rustling, and hundreds of multicoloured birdlike keys fluttered about the ceiling. The light from the enchanted windows, unbroken stained glass panes that stretched from floor to ceiling, was rosy and soft for all that they were underground, and the winged keys scattered rainbow spots over the smooth bright stone.

"Excuse me, but this just violates every possible rule of security. If you think you've secured a door with a lock, you keep the key safe and give it only to authorised entrants, you don't give the key wings and leave a broomstick propped against the wall. I know this place was made for first-years, but did that really not occur to anyone who came through here?"

"Perhaps you ought to give the Legion further lessons, General Chaos."

"Hmph. So how are we going to go through this one?"

"I assume you never tried out for Ravenclaw Seeker, Mr. Potter- it really is rather disconcerting to be glared at like that by an eleven-year-old. Well, as you insist."

The Professor drew his wand and touched it to his breast. With a drop of blood clinging to the end of his wand, he traced in the air a flaming rune, all jagged edges and malevolence, looking disturbingly wrong. Harry took a step back.

"Az-reth, az-reth, az-reth."

Twisting flames poured out from the rune, redder than blood and haloed in yellow-white and shot through with further black than midnight. The fire burned too brightly for its wine-dark shade of red, glared like the setting sun just as it touches the horizon, not quite unbearable to look at. The fire formed the shapes of dragons and lions and snakes, and they began to multiply and expand to fill the room. The heat blurred Harry's vision and crisped his hair. Sweat dripped from his forehead, but an icy chill ran up his spine. His dark side, or just plain instinct, was urging him to stay well away from the cursed fire.

Harry's Inner Ravenclaw suggested that the reason it looked so wrong was simple: in everyday experience, hot objects didn't usually glow that brightly in that shade of red due to the way black-body radiation behaved.

That explanation offered little comfort.

When Professor Quirrell locked eyes upon the Fiendfyre, it turned in on itself and shrank, taking the shape of a foul black-burning phoenix.

And something told Harry with burning certainty that if that balefire phoenix met Fawkes, the true phoenix would die and never be reborn.

The door burst into flames even before the false phoenix reached it; with a single sweep of its molten wings, the door vanished in a white flash, and the red-rimed doorway dripped stone. Professor Quirrell drifted sedately after the flames, the stone freezing in place as he passed.

Harry tried to turn to his dark side, which prompted a sudden thought. Only mostly Voldemort... His dark side, clearly, was the remaining influence of Lord Voldemort on his mind, thinking habits and feelings somehow leftover from imprinted memories that shouldn't have still existed.

Harry probably ought to have been more worried about turning out to be somehow partly the Dark Lord, but frankly that sounded a lot like something the hero agonised over for years, before finally realising that it was his choices that made him who he really was and that he obviously wasn't as evil as Voldemort.

Now that he knew what his dark side was, Harry thought he should be able to call on the icy calmness without falling into the less desirable parts of the pattern.

An ever-so-slightly cold Harry stepped over the threshold.

The vast chamber was torchlit this time. A few steps in front of Harry started a huge chessboard of black and white marble squares, each two metres or more on each side, stretching from wall to distant wall. Chess pieces almost the size of Hagrid stood on the board, intricately carven of granite, looking for all the world like well-made statues.

The room was high enough for the ceiling to be far out of reach of the statues.

Harry was about to suggest that the obvious solution was to simply fly over the board when he noticed that some of the pieces carried bows.

Professor Quirrell glanced at the board, and the black king and queen turned and stepped aside.

"Well," spoke Professor Quirrell, "since we still have four and a half hours until you leave the Quidditch game, it seems that we can afford to play. I am sure you are positively bursting with questions, and have done an admirable job keeping quiet. Take the king's place, and I shall take the queen's. Let us play, and I shall answer your questions if you have them."

Chapter 4: Playing Chess, Pt 3 — Cheating

The room after the one adjoining the chess room (which had revealed nothing of interest after the Fiendfyre bird had flown through) contained Potions equipment and ingredients, but Professor Quirrell produced a flask from his robes and poured it over the flames that had sprung up in the opposite doorway. He flicked his wand, and a number of ingredients vanished.

A wall of solid blackness had appeared in the doorway.

"Mr. Potter, when I dispel this barrier, you must remain beneath the True Cloak of Invisibility until I say so. That is a categorical order. Do you understand?"

Harry nodded, taking the Cloak from his pouch and pulling it over his shoulders.

"Ansswer in Parsseltongue."

"Sshall remain beneath Cloak until otherwisse ordered."

Professor Quirrell stooped down and pulled the corner of the Cloak over himself, standing as far away from Harry as possible. The sense of doom was more bearable now that Harry knew its provenance, but it was still uncomfortable.

Harry looked incredulously at Professor Quirrell. "Two people can wear the Cloak at once?!"

"It would appear so, yes. You already knew that it was not necessary for the Cloak to cover your entire body, did you not?"

Harry smacked the side of his own head, none too gently. That had been rather a lot of wasted effort in Azkaban.

The black barrier melted away.

The mirror in the centre of the room looked less like a mirror and more like a portal to a copy of the rooms behind Harry. It was framed in ornate gold, with wrought golden feet. The mirror did not look balanced, nor did it appear fixed to the floor. It was simply there, more solid by far than the walls and floor surrounding it, like a singular fixed and determined point relative to Earth's motion, no more moveable than the universe itself.

The Defence Professor gestured Harry around to the back of the mirror, which was plain gold, then hissed "It iss ssafe."

Harry stowed away the Cloak.

"This, Mr. Potter," said Professor Quirrell, taking on once more the tones of a lecturer, "is the last known surviving relic of Atlantis. Merlin called it the Mirror of Erised; Olga Xenda, supposed tutor of Baba Yaga, named it the Mirror of Vec; some scholars name it the Mirror of Noitilov; and a few scattered ancient records refer to it simply as Nillits."

"I take it you can't brute-force this one, Professor?"

Professor Quirrell smirked. "It is said that the Mirror of Noitilov perfectly reflects itself. It is the safest, most secure object in existence, having survived the Flood of Atlantis that wiped our forebears out of Time. It can be used to hide and trap objects and people, and it is where Dumbledore has hidden the Philosopher's Stone. No, Mr. Potter, I rather doubt Fiendfyre will have much of an effect upon it."

"What does it actually do?"

"It has perfect, unchallengeable power over all that it reflects, and can create alternate worlds, though only those as large as what it can reflect. Its power is supposedly based on the innermost feelings and desires of its viewer."

That didn't sound like a very satisfying explanation, and Harry said so.

The head tilted. "Hmm. Tell me, student of Muggle arts, what do the runes near the top of the Mirror say?"

The runes were simple, bold black lines and dots, curving gracefully and coming to abrupt, straight stops, looking quite unlike any writing system Harry had ever seen. Harry had had trouble enough with Latin. "I'm sorry, Professor, I don't recognise-"

"Read them anyway. Not dangerouss."

Harry looked once more at the runes, and opened his mouth. "Noitilov detalo partxe tnere hoc ruoy tu becafruoy ton wohsi." Harry looked away, blinking. That first rune was noitilov, and it meant what you detalo partxe so that it was tnere hoc -

It was almost impossible to describe: the runes didn't seem to relate to any other concepts, didn't form words in his head... Harry couldn't visualise the runes when he looked away, let alone transliterate them...

Harry shook his head and reinforced his Occlumency barriers, but felt the same effect.

"I take it you do not understand, then? A pity."

Harry had a sudden thought. "Voice recorder," he said to his pouch. Muggle technology didn't work very well at all in Hogwarts, as Harry's experiments had shown, but the pouch seemed to block or escape the magical field, and something this simple would take at least a few minutes to be severely affected - especially with Harry's own additions.

He read the runes aloud once more.

Harry turned his back on the Mirror and took a Quotes Quill from his pouch, then pressed the "play" button. The Quill scratched mechanically over a scrap of parchment.

Noitilov detalo partxe tnere hoc ruoy tu becafruoy ton wohsi.

"Um... 'I show not your face, but your coherent extrapolated volition.'"

Professor Quirrell was staring at him.

And then he began to laugh.

Harry had seen Professor Quirrell smile before, and give short, sardonic chuckles, but this was wild, genuine laughter, almost like Dumbledore had done when Harry had blackmailed him. Harry had never once expected to see the dignified and mysterious Defence Professor double over, clutching at his sides, but there he was.

Professor Quirrell collected himself with visible effort. "Ah, Mr. Potter," another chuckle, "I was about to say that it is known that even the greatest artefact can be defeated by a lesser, yet specialised counter-artefact," another burst of laughter, "and yet I never expected the last legacy of Atlantis to be brought low by a Muggle cassette tape."

Harry felt he was entirely justified in grinning smugly. Modern Muggles one, ancient Atlanteans zero.

"Well. That alone was worth the visit, and reaffirms what I suspected. The Mirror is a device intended to grant wishes, and to prevent the end of the world in such a way by showing a coherent extrapolation of the user's desire. Perhaps the Mirror transports those reflected therein to alternative universes... Or perhaps it simply traps people and objects in a point of time, as some tales describe. Now, Mr. Potter, to the task of retrieving the Stone."

The Defence Professor rolled up his sleeves, flicked his wand and said "Kulyok." A translucent, silvery-looking pouch appeared in the palm of his hand. "This pouc- pardon me, this pouch should collect anything the Mirror disgorges, and block any curse or contact poison applied." Quirrell grinned. "You see, there is a rather nasty potion known as Bahl's Stupefaction, of which Alastor Moody is fond. When contacted or imbibed, it has interesting effects on the cunning. The Dark Lady who called herself Lethae, dosed with such a potion, once kidnapped and attempted to interrogate one of her enemies in exchange for the lives of his friends. Her enemy was known to be clever and underhanded, so she confiscated all of his belongings down to the clothes on his back, abducted him to a graveyard of all places, went so far as to force him to make an Unbreakable Vow, made vivid and terrifying threats against all he loved, and raised wards against any conceivable intervention. Unfortunately, due to the Stupefaction she neglected to take his wand, and he shot her whilst she was busy monologuing."

Harry made a mental note to see if he could get Fred and George to slip some of that stuff into Draco's cornflakes.

Hidden beneath the Cloak, the two circled round to confront the Mirror of Erised.

OoOoO

The Mirror of Noitilov stood, solidly anchored - although, in fact, it looked more like the Mirror was anchoring the rest of the Universe. If Harry hadn't known that the Earth was in fact moving through space at enormous speeds, and more to the point that all motion was relative, he might have thought that all reality was centred on the Mirror.

"Do you have any ideas, Mr. Potter?"

Harry thought.

"Why is the Stone in the Mirror in the first place, Professor?" It would make some sense, and be exactly Dumbledore's style, to set up a vast system of incredibly easy traps guarding a Mirror that could show the viewer's heart's desire (which could be an excellent motivator for a student) and just so happened to also be the last legacy of Atlantis, the obvious and most secure hiding place for anything, and then actually keep the Philosopher's Stone in his sock drawer. Or, in fact, his pocket, so the would-be thief would have to duel Dumbledore...

"Do you know the history of Baba Yaga, child?"

"Only vaguely." After the school's reaction to her name at the beginning of the year, Harry had looked up the "undying" witch, and found standard fairy-tale fare. She had supposedly been a shapeshifting, immortal Dark Witch who had lived for centuries and vanished some time after teaching Battle Magic at Hogwarts. It was said that she devoured naughty children, which was used as a threat by parents of children too young to wonder what possible motive an immortal Dark Lady would have to enforce childhood discipline with cannibalism.

"Baba Yaga lived far longer than any other recorded witch or wizard, and there is evidence of her shifting forms at will, though she was never said to be a Metamorphmagus in her youth. She held the Stone of Permanence, obviously."

Actually, there was something more important...

"Professor, sorry to interrupt, but how is the Stone made? I saw an alchemical recipe-"

"A lie. Simple misdirection, intended to frame possession of the Stone as some earned right, to soften the blow." He scowled. "Magic is not permanent, as a general rule. One of the greatest feats of Merlin himself was the permanent Conjuration of the Most Ancient Hall of the Wizengamot, and he made no habit of such magic."

Professor Quirrell gave Harry a calculating look.

"The Stone was clearly intended as a healing device. In addition to its primary power, it can perform with a touch feats of healing beyond Muggles or wizards, delicate and obscenely complex and powerful healing magic. The Stone's abilities are eldritch even by my standards. Therefore, the Stone must be unique, and very old indeed."

"Oh." That was objectively the worst news Harry had heard in quite a while. He had entertained the prospect of some sort of mass-manufacture of Philosopher's Stones to provide immortality to the masses, and before learning what the Stone did, he'd even briefly wondered if anyone had ever actually tried to turn the Atlantic into Elixir of Life.

"Disappointing, I quite agree. Still, what magic has made, magic may yet make again. Regardless, some six centuries ago, Baba Yaga taught at Hogwarts. Lest she do any harm to the students or faculty, or they to her, an ancient device called the Goblet of Fire was used: Baba Yaga would spill none of the students' or faculty's blood, and take nothing of theirs, and they would extend her the same courtesy."

Professor Quirrell looked speculatively at the ornate edges of the Mirror.

"In her sixth year of Hogwarts was a beautiful, clever, horrifically evil witch named Perenelle. She seduced the Dark Lady over the months, and exhorted her to use her power of transformation to take the form of a man. The Goblet counted what followed as the shedding of Perenelle's blood and the taking of her virginity, and so Perenelle murdered the forsworn Dark Witch, and took for herself the Stone."

Professor Quirrell paused. "Of course, one does not survive six centuries without achieving at least a little cunning. Perhaps the entire story was concocted such that Baba Yaga could start a new life. It is entirely possible that that story, which took quite some effort to uncover, is merely another layer of misdirection, and that "Nicholas and Perenelle Flamel" are really Baba Yaga and Perenelle pretending to be Perenelle pretending to be both herself and her husband, and beyond that I cannot predict at what level she or they play."

"And the Mirror?"

"Ah, yes." Quirrell withdrew from his robes a golden sceptre, which should have been too large to fit. "I arranged for an inscription to be uncovered, claiming that this device could track the Stone wherever it lay, then carried out an ostentatious theft bearing the mark of Voldemort's hand. I believe the Stone's holder, whom I shall call Perenelle for the sake of brevity, insisted that the Mirror be used, which alone might evade even the greatest scrying."

"So Dumbledore hid it in the Mirror. What if only he can retrieve it?"

"The Mirror must be fair. It cannot be set to distinguish an individual. It can act only upon its viewer's hopes and dreams."

"How about, 'the individual must know that the password is- ' wait, no, it has to involve the viewer's wishes... Could the Mirror be set to only respond if the viewer's wishes perfectly align with Dumbledore's?"

Quirrell tapped his cheek. "Possibly. It seems unlikely, however, that the Mirror would be so exclusive..."

"Could you Confund yourself into being like Dumbledore?"

"Even if I could do so convincingly, the Mirror sees through such lesser effects. It is claimed that even Obliviation will not fool the Mirror. It would be utterly impossible to trick the Mirror by simply assuming Dumbledore's persona."

"Well, in what circumstances would Dumbledore want the Stone to be retrievable?

Quirrell looked as though he wanted to start pacing. "Mere circumstances will not matter to the Mirror - I begin to worry that this puzzle is insoluble. The Mirror must respond to a genuine volition, a true and heartfelt aspect of the viewer's real wishes, hopes, dreams, intentions... Ah. Ah."

The Defence Professor smiled unnervingly. He stepped out from under the Cloak and held out the translucent pouch in his left hand, gazing directly into the Mirror.

In the pouch, visible as though nothing were surrounding it, was a small chunk of shining scarlet stone, smooth and glassy and irregular. The pouch's appearance did not change upon contact with the Stone, but it somehow seemed more decisively real, fixed and solid.

That's not fair, complained Ravenclaw. How did he-

Then the Professor vanished, but his reflection in the Mirror remained, alongside another one.

"Hello, David," said Albus Dumbledore.

Author's Note:

Seemss to me that ssubreddit'ss collective intelligencce sshould be ssufficcient to guess meanss of taking Sstone from Mirror with cluess given. Yess, Parsseltongue hass word for "ssubreddit".

Chapter 5: Smoke and Mirrors

"Hello, David," said Albus Dumbledore calmly. The old wizard's eyes glinted like sapphires. His robes were a deep indigo-purple, padded and seeming to follow his movements closely, such that they would not obstruct him. Fawkes perched on his shoulder, space-black eyes shining with righteous courage, like an unwavering flame. In Dumbledore's right hand was a long, slender wand of dark-grey wood, in his left the Line of Merlin Unbroken, and his magic was gathered about him like a cloak.

"Albus," replied the Defence Professor, inclining his head. David Monroe's icy eyes met the Chief Warlock's unflinchingly, his robes dark and reserved, a creature of cursed fire behind him, his own wand in his hand.

Dumbledore's eyes gave the sudden impression of X-raying the Defence Professor. "I have kept my promise, Quirinus, to make no enquiry into your identity, and yet one cannot help what one sees. It was Harry Potter's nature that convinced me, in the end." The eyes twinkled, and he spoke as though conversing over drinks. " I was most amused to find the boy forged in Lord Voldemort's image before me, blackmailing me for the sake of his fellow students. Such dark intellect, harnessed for the sake of Lily and James and Michael and Petunia's warmth and love! Tom, in his hubris, created a good Voldemort to oppose him."

Monroe did not look like he was enjoying a casual conversation. "It rather speaks volumes," he said dryly, "that it took Voldemort's own help for you to have a chance to defeat him."

Dumbledore smiled. "Oft evil will shall evil mar, as Tolkien put it. I wonder what Harry made of that observation... you two really are quite alike, you know."

Monroe smirked. "I shall take that as a compliment. Just this day I have seen our young associate unravel the Words of False Comprehension. Oh, and we two were the ones who seized Bellatrix Black from Azkaban."

Dumbledore nodded. If he was surprised at either revelation, he did not show it. "My own Patronus identified Harry's as the one that it detected in Azkaban. May I ask your intended purpose?"

Dumbledore's calmness and politeness would have set Harry on edge before, but he recognised that impulse as a habit inherited from Riddle, and discounted it.

There was a definite edge to Quirrell's voice. "Yes, you who would never think of sharpening a Hufflepuff's bones into spears." He reached into his robes and drew forth a bone-white wand that seemed horribly familiar, with a black ribbon tied around it. Thirteen and a half inches, yew, phoenix feather core... "I sought to find where Bellatrix had hidden the Dark Lord's wand. If it comes to it, I shall use a Portkey to drop it into the central pit of Azkaban."

Professor Dumbledore raised his eyebrows. "I would call that inhumane, for any other than he."

Quirrell's tone was acid. "Inhumane. And yet you withhold the Philosopher's Stone from the world. Yes, Mr. Potter accompanied me here, because copies of the Dark Lord or not, we both at least comprehend the elementary ethical axiom that death is bad."

The old wizard sighed. "Quirinus, the Stone, please."

"Ah." There was no shift in the stance of either of the two, but there was sudden danger in the air. "You truly do not know what the Stone does, then. Frank and Alice-"

"I am resolved," said the Chief Warlock with iron in his tone, "to deafen myself to such claims, for Tom is too persuasive and too cunning for my judgement to be secure."

Professor Quirrell passed a hand over his eyes. "That is madness. There is a reason we call such paranoia an illness-"

In mid-sentence, the Defence Professor aimed his wand.

It happened before Harry could react, before he could shout a warning, before he could form the words of the Patronus Charm.

The Killing Curse struck Albus Dumbledore squarely in the chest.

The old wizard did not blink.

Fawkes spread his wings and cawed, the warm yet warning cry of the true phoenix. The dark-grey wand rose in front of Dumbledore like a sword, a wave of white fire ran up it and burst from the tip in a shower of sparks, and it was like Harry heard a sudden song, a paean of glory and battle, a hymn of victory.

The Hallowed Wand. Whilst he held that, Dumbledore was no more vulnerable than a Dementor - that was the part of Death's power bound into the Elder Wand.

The Peverells had had a taste for flashiness, it seemed.

Harry had thought he'd seen advanced magic before, but this he couldn't follow at all, it was just too far over his head, though he noted that Quirrell was moving like a Muggle martial artist but with inhuman grace, hissing echoing Words of Power, whereas Dumbledore was mostly standing his ground, occasionally waving the Elder Wand or murmuring something that would always overcome Quirrell's magic and show him gritting his teeth and gripping his own wand with both hands to resist.

Quirrell gestured, and the black-red-white false phoenix hissed and streaked at Fawkes.

Horror-struck, Harry waited for the creature of life and rebirth to be cursed into permanent death.

Fawkes screamed, and Professor Quirrell staggered. Dumbledore bellowed something ancient and terrible, and suddenly Fawkes was sheathed in golden fire, and he met his mockery in midair, talons blazing.

Quirrell began to incant something incomprehensible, cold and harrowing, but Dumbledore made a cutting motion and the rising sense of power vanished.

"The most powerful wizard alive" had most certainly not been an exaggeration.

Even if Harry had been able to make himself heard over the noise of the duel, even if the Mirror had let sound through in that direction, he wouldn't have known what to say. Shut up and multiply - if Quirrell gets the Stone it could save hundreds of thousands of lives -

Do we trust Quirrell? asked Slytherin.

Dumbledore doesn't know what the Stone does. Maybe he'd allow it to be used in a hospital if he did, argued Gryffindor.

Dumbledore raised his wand and swung it like a cricket bat, speaking words with sounds he shouldn't have been able to make and Harry shouldn't have been able to hear. The force of the resulting spell was such that Harry felt it even through the Mirror, setting his teeth on edge and his hair on end. Quirrell's eyes widened, and he was forced to conjure a burnished silver shield, which showed no sign of damage when the spell struck, but rang with a pure, chilling note.

With a bolt of quicksilver and a sound like gunshot, Quirrell managed to force Dumbledore onto his back foot, but it was obviously hopeless. Quirrell had Slytherin's lore, and all the Dark Lord's hoarded knowledge on top of that, but Dumbledore was even more skilful, not to mention invulnerable.

"Singularis Nex!"

"Lux Argentus."

A bolt of white lightning impacted upon a mote of pure blackness, which swelled and burst, reforming into a swarm of daggers that converged on Quirrell, who popped like a soap bubble and appeared by his opponent's side. He waved his wand and Dumbledore was surrounded by a vast sphere of solid steel, glowing with enchantment, which Quirrell tapped with the Philosopher's Stone.

For the briefest moment, Harry thought Monroe might have won.

Then the shell glowed cherry-red and white-hot, and the solid steel consumed itself. Fawkes gave a victorious cry, and shredded the false phoenix into scattered flames. The scraps of Fiendfyre danced ineffectively around Dumbledore.

"It was foolish of you to try this, David," came the old voice, gently.

"Think you can last another twenty hours, Albus?" spat Monroe.

Lose, Professor, begged Harry silently, if there's ever a time to lose it's when the enemy is literally invincible...

With a whip-cracking motion, a line of fire impacted Quirrell's shields and slammed him into the Mirror-wall. Dumbledore advanced on him, wand level.

The Defence Professor vanished, and did not reappear.

What the-

PAIN.

Darkness coiled around Harry, holding him and binding him so deeply that he didn't know where he ended and the darkness began.

Harry doubled over, crying out, and then it was over as Quirrell reappeared next to him, covered too by the Cloak of Invisibility, subject no more to the Mirror's power.

Harry could feel it, feel the magic start to resonate, but it was nothing like as bad as in Azkaban. Possession doesn't count as being anywhere near as powerful as the Killing Curse, clearly.

Quirrell slashed his wand like a dagger over his left wrist, and his hand winked out of existence and in its place arose a shimmering red barrier over the Mirror of Erised.

The shreds of Fiendfyre burned through the wall of Hogwarts and up through the earth.

The sense of doom, previously muted, rose to intolerable heights as Quirrell's arm linked around Harry's, shielded only by robes, and then they shot out and up through the tunnel, taking them beyond Hogwarts' wards.

Distantly, Harry heard Dumbledore shatter Quirrell's ward, and the old wizard reappeared, borne up by Fawkes-

A tug behind his navel, and the world vanished.

Chapter 7: The Snake and the Dog

Sirius leapt out of his chair so quickly that Harry barely saw him move. His wand, which had never left his hand, was pointed squarely at the Defence Professor's heart.

"Um, Sirius, that's an extremely bad idea," Harry said in growing alarm.

"Who are you?" demanded Sirius. He made no movements and spoke no spells, but Harry could see faint ripples, distortions in the air like a heat-haze, as magic layered itself around Sirius.

"He's not wrong, you know," said the Defence Professor idly, leaning against the wall.

"Answer the question," growled Sirius.

Quirrell looked distinctly unimpressed. "Professor Quirinus Quirrell. And put that wand away before you have someone's eye out with it."

"Is he with you, Harry?" Sirius asked in a controlled voice, never taking his eyes off Professor Quirrell, who was inspecting his fingernails.

"He is. And if he meant me any harm, I'd be dead by now."

Sirius hesitated, then sheathed his wand.

"Well. Sirius Black, the great traitor and mass-murderer. How did you manage to escape Azkaban, then?"

"None of your business."

"As truculent as ever, I see."

There was a moment of silence.

"So, what now?" Harry ventured.

"We leave this place at once. We are most fortunate that Dumbledore has not arrived already. Then-"

"Hold on," Sirius interrupted. "Where exactly are you taking Harry?"

"That," Quirrell retorted sharply, "is of no concern to you."

Harry tried and failed to think of something to say to dissipate the rising tension.

Something about Sirius's stance changed in a way that Harry's brain translated to a dog raising its hackles. "I happen to be his godfather."

Paying no notice, Professor Quirrell produced another Portkey from within his robes and tossed it to Harry. Wordlessly, he turned and stalked towards the half-rotten door, beckoning Harry with one hand.

Harry made to follow him.

Sirius reappeared before the door, and his wand was out again. "Where do you think you're going?"

Professor Quirrell closed his eyes briefly. "One perceives that the expression 'like a dog with a bone' is well-founded."

"I make the jokes around here, scaly."

"Professor?" asked Harry. "Why not just bring him with us?"

Sirius nodded firmly.

The Defence Professor gave Sirius an appraising look.

Finally, Professor Quirrell sighed. "Very well. I confess that I am curious about our canine companion's story. Now, must I remind the two of you that we are still in enemy territory?" Quirrell stepped smartly outside the Shack, past the boundary of the wards. He seized Sirius' wrist, and Harry noticed his godfather's hand tighten almost imperceptibly on his wand. Quirrell reached into his robes, nodded to Harry, and vanished.

Harry activated his own Portkey.

The evening air was crisp and clear. The Moon rose above the horizon, and a faint wash of stars was visible already.

Professor Quirrell waved his wand, and a ball of light appeared in midair, revealing a small, deserted farmhouse and a decrepit barn.

"Where are we?" asked Sirius warily.

"A deserted farm in Devon. It should do for our purposes tonight."

Professor Quirrell's voice had grown abruptly weaker, and he led them towards the barn with an irregular gait.

For a moment, it seemed to be an ordinary, empty barn. Then something bent and warped in the air, and it expanded tenfold, revealing a warm, spacious, well-lit room. There were countless shelves bearing potions ingredients, spare wands, odd-looking bits of jewellery, and several strange devices Harry didn't recognise. In the centre of the room, there was a groaning, rumbling noise, and a black altar surrounded by six black pillars arose from the floor.

"Well," said Professor Quirrell, "first things first."

Quirrell pressed his wand to himself, and suddenly he seemed to stand taller. His hairline spread out and forwards, his skin lost its pallor, and new flesh filled out his sickly, thin limbs.

Quirrell reached into his pocket and withdrew the Philosopher's Stone. For a moment, he held still; then he raised it to the light and examined it speculatively. For a moment, Harry thought he might have seen a grid of intricately-arranged points within it, but then the sight was gone.

Sirius seemed to be about to say something. Quirrell turned towards him, and then his hand darted forwards, passing cleanly through Sirius' shields, and touched the Philosopher's Stone to him.

It might have been a trick of the light, but the haunted, hollow look in Sirius's eyes seemed to ease, and he stepped back, blinking. "What just-"

Harry furrowed his brow. How did the Stone even know what Professor Quirrell wanted it to do? And how can a rock know how to fix a human brain?

Quirrell smiled thinly. "Mr. Black, would you mind awfully explaining how you came to be out of Azkaban, and by all appearances not in fact a Death Eater?"

Sirius paused for a moment, nonplussed, then shrugged and began to tell his story. The words seemed to come to him more easily this time.

Quirrell raised his wand and traced a human shape in midair.

A man's body, cloaked in fine and flowing robes, spun into existence before the Defence Professor, held magically upright. The body's eyes were closed, and it did not breathe.

Quirrell tapped it with the Stone, then flicked his wand. From his pockets arose an assortment of objects Harry didn't recognise, which secreted themselves in the conjured body's pockets. The Defence Professor touched the body's limbs with his wand, tracing a line from shoulder to elbow, elbow to wrist, hip to knee, knee to foot, murmuring incantations.

At length, Sirius's story came to an end.

"Fal. Tor. Pan."

An echoing thunderclap pierced the air, and Professor Quirrell's body collapsed to the floor.

The conjured body's eyes opened, and they were the same shade as Quirrell's.

David Monroe's new body looked like Quirinus Quirrell's, but with deliberate mistakes. There were the same sharp features, the same icy eyes, but he seemed younger than he had all year, and somehow more clearly and decidedly present. Professor Quirrell stretched slowly, examining his new hands, opening and closing his fingers. "Obliviate," he said to the man on the floor, and his voice had all of its customary dry precision.

"Um," said Sirius, seeming to remember that he was an ostensibly-responsible member of the Order of the Phoenix, "should I be doing something about this?"

The original Quirinus Quirrell stirred feebly. "Free," he gasped.

"Ah, Mr. Quirrell," said the Defence Professor. "My apologies for the theft of your body." A lazy flick of the wand, and a coin purse appeared in Quirinus's hands, which Monroe tapped with the Stone. "Please accept this as my payment." Monroe muttered some kind of diagnostic spell, then nodded, seeming satisfied. Monroe offered his hand. The original Quirinus Quirrell took it and stood, slowly, incredulously, then turned and vanished with a dull pop.

David Monroe - Harry decided that it would be easier to just keep thinking of him as Professor Quirrell - turned back. "The time is come, Mr. Potter. Lay your ring upon the altar, dispel the Transfiguration, and I shall restore life as best I can. Sshe sshall not be harmed in any manner, but resstored to true and lassting life."

Heart hammering in his chest, Harry bent down and untied his shoelaces, ignoring something Sirius was spluttering about something or other being impossible. Carefully, he withdrew the solid-diamond ring and laid it upon the black marble altar.

"Finite incantatem."

Two-thirds of a corpse sprawled across the ebon stone, so cold and pale in death, standing out in sharp relief against the blackness.

Harry glanced away, holding himself together, pushing away all the memories, trying to ignore the image.

Professor Quirrell glided smoothly forwards and waved a hand over the body. Hermione's body straightened and oriented itself, clothed in new Hogwarts robes, unstained by blood or spellfire, and then Professor Quirrell pointed his wand and new flesh streamed forwards, reshaping itself into restored limbs.

Behind Harry, Sirius gave out a choked yell and made to approach the Defence Professor.

"Stay back," said Quirrell, perfectly calmly. "This procedure is exceedingly complex." He pointed his wand at the obelisks, and they began to chant in deep, echoing tones that Harry thought sounded vaguely like Greek.

Hermione's body started to become less pale, less twisted, seeming almost asleep.

"Harry," came Sirius's voice, gently, too gently, "I'm sorry, but she's not coming back. Don't get your hopes up. Whatever your... friend is trying to do, it won't work. The closest he could get is an Inferius, and that's the last thing anyone would-"

"Prediction noted," Harry managed. "She's not- her brain should be OK. I used- I used Muggle knowledge to keep her brain safe after she died, and she's been kept mostly static by the Transfiguration, and we have the Stone..."

Sirius laid a hand on Harry's shoulder. "I'm not going to patronise you, Harry. She's dead. Her soul has moved on. She's never coming back."

"And what if she does?" Harry said suddenly. "Does that mean she won't have a soul? What do you actually expect to see?"

Sirius was silent for a moment. Then he looked intently at Harry. "Well... if she does, and she is who she always was, then a lot of people are very, very wrong."

"Muggles can already bring people back from the dead sometimes. There are people whose hearts have stopped, and Muggle healing can make them start again. Not always, but sometimes."

Sirius looked thoughtful, and said no more.

Hermione's body was surrounded by a pale-blue glow, which Professor Quirrell had said would keep her perfectly static and preserved.

The Defence Professor turned and vanished upon the spot. A few moments later he reappeared, stowing a Time-Turner away under his robes. In his hand were two pebbles, one white and one black.

"What was all that about?"

The Defence Professor was humming a small tune to himself.

"The Philosopher's Stone, as it turns out, Mr. Potter, is very useful. All will become clear."

Quirrell took a piece of oddly bright white chalk from one of his pockets, and began to trace a circle on the floor, adding careful, precise flourishes that glimmered oddly in the magical light.

"There is an old ritual that can sacrifice a magical creature to transfer its magical nature to one within the circle. Transfiguration sickness is a tricky business, and there is no use in taking chances. Besides, I would really rather not go through all this again."

Amid the other questions that were competing for priority, Harry remembered one in particular.

"Professor? May I just ask, when you were in the Mirror with the Headmaster, why didn't you just show him what the Stone can do?"

Professor Quirrell did not look up from where he was drawing the circle on the floor.

"The Dark Lord planned," he began, "that Voldemort should lose. He was mindful of the mistakes of the Dark Evangel, who tried to introduce herself as the 'Walking Catastrophe' and 'Apostle of Darkness', but panicked and called herself the 'Apostrophe of Darkness'. And so when his walking joke of a Dark Lord was seen as a serious threat, he lost any respect for Dumbledore, and to a certain degree I suppose that influenced me."

"Why were you influenced by Voldemort in the first place?" Sirius interjected. "And how do you know-"

"I am partly Voldemort, Mr. Black."

There was silence for a moment, then Sirius shook his head. "You know what? Fine. Of course you are."

"The Dark Lord used incredibly dark magic to copy his mind onto mine. No, I am not as evil as he. If you would like to hear the details, please feel free to never ask about it again."

Quirrell still didn't look up from his inscription.

"As I was saying, you discovered for yourself, Mr. Potter, that it is a personal flaw of Riddle's that he consistently underestimates other people. Well, 'underestimate' is not quite accurate: he does not consider other people to be players of the game in any respect. Your failure in your first battle against Sunshine was, in part, your heritage from Riddle. And so it did not occur to me at the time to try to reason with Dumbledore."

Professor Quirrell stood up, and turned to regard Hermione. He raised his wand and the circle flared brightly. A thought seemed to strike the Defence Professor, and he tapped the line of the circle with the Stone. "Finite," he then said to the circle.

The circle of brightness remained, and Quirrell made a pleased sound. "That proves that. The Stone makes magic a fixture in such a way that it is as though there is no magic at all. This circle is magical, and yet it cannot be dispelled because there is nothing to dispel. "

From his hand fell the two pebbles, and they landed in the circle and swelled into the shapes of a unicorn and a mountain troll.

Before Harry could even begin to process this, Quirrell pointed his wand at the two creatures and muttered, "Thuo tei dunamei," then slashed it towards Hermione.

The two creatures crumbled to dust, and then that too faded from sight.

"Transfiguration sickness is nothing before a troll's healing, and a unicorn's blood will preserve life even at the brink of death. Miss Granger will suffer no ill effects, but live as though she always had that power. No lesser force or magic shall slay her."

"Thank you," whispered Harry. The Defence Professor was clearly in a very good mood.

Professor Quirrell nodded, and Harry didn't quite catch the odd look in his eyes.

"Now, the first problem: this is the enchanted body of a dead Muggle. The brain could be awakened rather easily, perhaps, but I do not know if her own magic would return."

"I did some research," said Harry's lips automatically, "and I think magic is probably just passed on by a marker gene. Coming back to life shouldn't change that."

"Perhaps. I am not convinced... There may be a better solution." Professor Quirrell glanced towards Sirius. "Sacrificing a wizard to this ritual is a possibility-" Professor Quirrell caught Harry's sharp look, and rolled his eyes. "Very well. There exists another ritual that would solve the matter, but finding her enemy's blood, father's bone and servant's flesh would take time."

"Let me try something," Harry said, struck by a sudden thought. He stepped forwards and raised his wand to point at Hermione.

Harry pushed down the joy that was slowly mounting. It wasn't enough, wasn't good enough. There were still people dying even as Harry tried to save this one. Dozens, hundreds, thousands, millions, billions who had already been lost. Billions more, who would have done whatever it took, torn reality apart to bring that someone back.

They had failed, or never dared to try, or hope. Most of the world, even the magical world, had come to the conclusion that death was inevitable. The prospect of resurrection had barely even crossed their minds.

"Professor," said Harry, "this might work better if I can see the stars."

Quirrell gave a single nod, and spoke the spell of the Silent Night.

Harry stood in the depths of the sky, lit by the unwavering light of countless stars.

It hadn't quite struck him before. Here, tonight, beneath the starlight, he would begin. He had already resolved to end death, but that wasn't enough, nowhere near enough. Death should not be, he thought, and never should have been. There was hope, here, in this world of Time-Turners and Philosopher's Stones and phoenixes.

Harry would not stop with saving the living. He would not stop with saving Hermione.

Harry would not stop until he had saved every single one, wizard or witch or Muggle or house-elf or goblin or centaur or anything else he couldn't imagine, rescued everyone who had ever fallen into Death's hands.

Harry would not stop until he realised that dream, until he could watch the Sun go out alongside every single person the human species - and any other thinking species - had ever lost.

We don't have to put up with it. Nobody, ever, will have to spare a moment to think about the ones who died before they could be helped. I refuse to lose, or to have lost.

"Expecto, PATRONUM!"

And there was light.

Hermione Granger took her first breath for the second time.

Hermione's body was bathed in silver fire, even as Harry staggered. Some of the life and magic he'd just lost would never return to him, he knew. It wasn't much, barely even noticeable, but what he had lost would never return. That sacrifice was permanent.

Professor Quirrell touched Hermione's forehead with the Stone, and though Harry's Patronus faded away, some of that silver fire yet remained about her.

The sphere of stars slowly faded away.

And then two unfamiliar voices spoke, "Avada Kedavra."

Harry Potter and David Monroe collapsed to the floor, dead.

Chapter 8: Shut Up And Multiply, Pt 1

Sirius Black was feeling distinctly out of his depth.

He didn't know his godson. Dumbledore had offered to introduce him to Harry before, but he'd refused. The boy had never known his parents - thanks to you, said the voice that even the supposed Philosopher's Stone hadn't silenced - and Sirius hadn't thought he'd want to meet the man who'd consigned them to death.

And now here Harry was, and everything was happening so quickly - better than Sirius had thought it would, he'd thought Harry would hate him, but even so...

Sirius burst through the doors of Godric's Hollow, horror rising inside him. It took him three tries to cast Lumos.

The ceiling had sagged dangerously, and the centre had given way entirely. The room was caked in plaster dust, and a liquid that seemed black as pitch in the wandlight.

James Potter lay somehow untouched by rubble, his glasses still on, spread-eagled. His wife lay some distance away from him, on top of the collapsed ceiling, the splinters of her wand still clutched in broken fingers.

It was easier than it had ever been for Sirius to turn his mind away. Ever since "Quirinus Quirrell" (though as far as Sirius was concerned, if that was the man's real name, his was Elvendork) had used what was apparently the Philosopher's Stone on him, he'd felt more whole somehow, and certain memories were staying at the back of his mind where they belonged. Happier thoughts were coming to him more easily now than they had since before Azkaban.

He had thought about what Harry was trying to do now, after that night, in a manner of speaking. He'd wanted to make James' and Lily's deaths not have happened, but he had never really thought that he could do anything after the fact.

Harry cast the Patronus Charm, and Sirius felt a surge of pride - it was an extremely advanced spell for an eleven-year-old.

It should have been impossible, but the girl was breathing.

"Vitalis Revelio," Sirius murmured.

She was alive.

Quirrell was still looking absently at some part of the floor, which had shown a cluster of stars, his mind clearly elsewhere.

At that moment, Sirius's ears popped, and he felt the unmistakable sensation of an Anti-Apparition Jinx failing. He frowned. The Jinx on this place was only one-way, so there was no reason for Quirrell to-

"Avada Kedavra!"

The Killing Curse hit Quirrell in the back from point-blank range.

Sirius dived aside in an agile motion, firing curses in an indiscriminate arc.

The bolts bent in mid-air and curved around the figures of two unfamiliar women.

The first was dark-haired and pale, wrapped in a heavy black felt cloak of an unrecognisable style. She held no wand, but bore in her hand a dark staff of twisted wood. Her face was young, but her eyes were deep, dark and old. Despite her physical youth, she gave off an impression of terrible age, an ancient quality that whispered of forgotten magic and old curses.

Beside her was a woman who looked just as youthful. She was blonde and willowy, and held a long and slender wand. Despite her unassuming appearance, the sense of magic about her was strong, and her grey eyes were cold and sharp.

Sirius glanced back towards the altar, and his heart stopped.

His godson, Harry James Potter, lay on the ground. His eyes were open and glassy, his mouth open, glasses askew. He looked almost exactly like James Potter had, that night-

"Recognise this one, Perry?" asked the dark-haired figure.

"No. Might as well- ah!"

Sirius roared and loosed a blistering bolt of lightning at the woman, who stepped back and barely caught it on the end of her wand.

The blonde recovered quickly and slashed her own wand.

Sirius staggered backwards, snarling, a chunk of his shielding torn away. He rolled his shoulders and adjusted his grip. He was out of practice, but he had once been able to out-duel Mad-Eye two times out of three. Harry's murderers would not escape alive.

The dark-haired one paid no attention. She gestured at Quirrell's body, and a wand rose up from it and flew into her hand. A black ribbon tied to it vanished in a flash of flame.

Sirius circled his left hand, and a blue haze arose before him. He dodged left and brought his wand around in a wide sweep-

The blonde witch clicked her fingers and suddenly Sirius was flat on his back, winded. He sprang to his feet and rolled aside, hurling curses that winked out of existence or splashed harmlessly against shields.

Then the older-seeming witch tapped her staff on the ground and disrupted most of his wards. Sirius ducked another Killing Curse and barely blocked an unfamiliar brown hex. This was insane, there were barely a dozen wizards in the entire world on this power level-
His fingers numbed on his wand as he struggled to parry another curse.

He set his teeth. He wasn't ready to join James and Lily - and Harry, he thought with another burst of guilt - just yet.

"Remembering why we retired, B?" asked the blonde idly. "It's just no fun any more."

There was a white-blue flash, and Sirius dropped to one knee helplessly, his resolve gone. It was hopeless. It was almost like trying to fight Dumbledore.

Darkness began to build around the edges of his vision.

OoOoO

He was underwater, and underground, and on fire, and in the sky, and amongst the stars...

Harry felt a sensation that he recognised from the Cloak of Invisibility, like touching his wand for the first time, like an inaudible song.

For a single absurd moment, Harry thought he might have been in the afterlife.

Then his brain caught up to him. So this is what a Horcrux feels like.

The adrenaline - well, Harry didn't have adrenaline any more, but that was still what it felt like - was fading away. With a jolt, Harry realised that the stars were all around him, all three-hundred and sixty degrees.

May I point out, said Harry's Inner Slytherin, that we just DIED?

It was difficult to have any sense of immediacy, here amongst the stars.

Mr. Potter?

Professor? Is that you? said Harry in his thoughts. The phrase that came to him to describe the experience was "thinking loudly". Harry could sense the Horcrux system now, notice Professor Quirrell's presence.

I can't imagine who else you might have been expecting! There was a definite sense of agitation in Quirrell's... thought? It is imperative that we return NOW. I suggest-

I have an idea.

Harry focussed on the inaudible song of the Resurrection Stone in the back of his mind, and visualised the scene in Professor Quirrell's workshop, willing himself to be present.

OoOoO

Sirius slammed everything he had into the strongest shield he could to block an area-effect curse.

Sirius! sounded Harry's voice. Let me in!

What?!

JUST DO IT!

It was unmistakably Harry, and even if it wasn't Sirius didn't exactly have anything to lose. He consciously relaxed his defences-

OoOoO

Inhabiting his godfather's body was a strange experience. He was too tall, and the wand didn't suit him-

Harry aimed Sirius' wand at Professor Quirrell's body, remembered Hermione's resurrection, and shouted, "Expecto Patronum!"

It felt almost sacrilegious using the Patronus Charm so casually, as a combat tactic, but Harry's inner models of Alastor Moody and Professor Quirrell were glaring at him for that thought.

The magic had flowed from Harry, not Sirius. Interesting, said Ravenclaw, that implies-

SHUT UP, hissed the rest of Harry.

Sirius's shield fell, and two curses winged towards him.

They burst into rainbow sparks as the Defence Professor rushed forwards through the air like a ghost given form.

Harry pointed Sirius's wand again, and cast the Patronus Charm at himself.

Harry woke up in his own body. No magic had been lost, that time, but it hadn't been pleasant. C-L-O-A-K, he signed in his pouch, and drew the Cloak of Invisibility over himself.

Behind him, discreetly, wards rose up around the altar where Hermione lay.

That seemed... too nice for Professor Quirrell...

A dark-haired witch rolled her eyes. "This one won't stay dead either, then." Her accent was ever-so-slightly unusual, not quite identifiable. She looked young, but she had a sort of air of age that felt like some kind of magic...

"You Riddles are like bloody cockroaches," muttered the blonde, fingering her wand. "Any idea how they're managing it, B?"

"B" shrugged.

Horror was slowly dawning in Harry.

What am I seeing?

Two powerful Dark witches, young-looking but old-seeming, who showed up immediately after Professor Quirrell stole the Philosopher's Stone...

"Of course, one does not survive six centuries without acquiring at least a little cunning..."

Harry looked over to Sirius Black, who was kneeling down, holding onto his wand in one hand and his head in the other.

Harry wasn't convinced that even Professor Quirrell could defeat Baba Yaga and Perenelle Flamel together.

OoOoO

Quirrell whirled in midair, past a barrage of magic, firing Killing Curses mixed with spells Harry couldn't recognise in a constant stream. Quirrell's hidden workshop was already blasted to pieces, the wooden walls incinerated or in some cases somehow melted, looking more like old candle wax than wood. The moonlight glowed faintly over the battleground.

Killing Curses flashed against Quirrell time and again, but he paid no mind. The Patronus, Harry realised with a jolt. Professor Quirrell had been holding the Stone when Harry had cast his spell. Thinking about it, it was odd that that hadn't triggered the resonance - although technically, the spell had been cast at a dead body, and the Stone had rendered it non-magical.

"Expecto Patronum," Harry murmured once more, and the silver figure burst into existence, just in case any stray Killing Curses came towards him or Sirius.

Professor Quirrell jabbed his wand into the sky like a sword, and suddenly all of reality seemed to focus on one point of baleful blue at the end of his wand.

There was a deep, resounding note, and then the two witches' shields splintered and they were blown backwards onto the grass.

Harry was forcibly reminded once more just how unbalanced the power ladder was. How does magical power even work?

The blonde - Perenelle, presumably - rolled out of the way of a Killing Curse and loosed a jet of pitch blackness at Professor Quirrell, who dismissed it with a flick of the hand.

The other witch made a circling motion with her staff, and Harry's limbs felt suddenly heavy.

Quirrell plunged out of the sky, but then he seemed to fall faster than gravity would have pulled him, and he slammed into the ground.

The earth burst up around the Defence Professor, throwing Harry off his feet so hard that a Muggle would have broken bones. The altar alone remained entirely undisturbed, but the ground shuddered and creaked as far around as Harry could see.

Now he's just showing off, muttered Harry's Inner Critic (which had decided that other Tom Riddle copies were fair game).

The earthquake had caught the two witches off-guard, and Quirrell shot back up into the sky and kept up his pattern of Killing Curses, simultaneously loosing other magic that seemed beyond even them.

The Killing Curse, Professor Quirrell had once told Harry, was amongst the most useful spells in existence, but not the be-all and end-all of duelling. It was invariably lethal and unblockable, true, but it was also extremely easy to dodge, being relatively slow-moving and bright green. Additionally, even if one happened to be sufficiently indifferent to cast it repeatedly, it was quite a serious drain on one's magic.

Even despite this, Quirrell's newfound immunity to the Killing Curse and "mysterious" powers of flight seemed to be letting him hold his own against both witches at the same time.

Baba Yaga and Perenelle spoke the same incantation together, reminding Harry uncomfortably of what the Weasley twins had tried against the troll, and Professor Quirrell was forced to raise a white circular ward to block it.

In that brief opening, Baba Yaga touched one finger to her arm and hissed "Innervate."

Harry's scar burned.

The world flashed sickly yellow, and Professor Quirrell was flicked sharply through the air, dipping dangerously before managing to stabilise himself.

That was when Harry saw the most terrifying thing he had ever seen.

Professor Quirrell looked frightened.

Harry turned around.

And Harry realised what a complete idiot he'd been. He'd been in the Horcrux system, and hadn't realised what was missing. Riddles, the blonde woman had said, and she hadn't been talking about Harry...

Hermione Granger was standing, pointing a bone-white wand at Professor Quirrell, smiling widely, her eyes shining, ever-so-faintly, crimson.

The Dark Lord had risen again.